<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Secure Shell">

	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Extended Package for SSH Server and Client Functionality</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>0.8</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>24 August 2015</issuedate>
		<approver/>
		<supercedes/>
	</intro>

	<section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
		<!-- This section sets the context for not only the ESR, but what is 
			expected of the resulting Protection Profile (PP). The intent is 
			that the remaining sections provide succinct statements that 
			highlight the relevant aspects to be addressed by the Technical 
			Community (TC) constructing the PP. Here, the authors provide a 
			narrative that introduces the reader to the problem being solved, 
			and presents key aspects that support or guide the TC, and may
			elaborate on subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level
			statements.
		-->
		Secure Shell (SSH) is an encrypted network protocol for initiating shell sessions
		between a client and a server. An SSH session allows a user to interact with the remote system
		via a text-based shell. Typically SSH is used to perform privileged tasks on 
		remote machines.
		<br/>
		This essential security requirements (ESR) document outlines the high-level
		security requirements for an SSH Client or Server, which will be expressed in a Common Criteria 
		Extended Package (EP). These requirements address threats within a scope established 
		by use cases and environment assumptions. 
		<br/>
		The security functionality must be realistic and achievable by commercially available 
		products. The resulting EP will also include objective and repeatable evaluation activities, 
		so that evaluations can be executed in a timely manner.
		<br/>
		With regard to evaluation scope, the SSH Client or Server itself is composed of the software 
		that is delivered to the end user in the SSH product. This typically includes
		a user mode application, covered by the Application Software Protection Profile and this
		SSH Extended Package. An SSH Client or Server could also be delivered as part of 
		an Operating System which could include user mode or kernel mode components. In this 
		case the SSH Client or Server would be covered by either the General Purpose Operating 
		System Protection Profile or the Mobile Device Fundamentals Protection Profile 
		and this SSH Extended Package.
		
	</section>

	<section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
		<!-- 
			This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the 
			security problem by providing the reader with concise statements 
			regarding the scenarios in which the technology is being used. The 
			intended usage presented here should lay the groundwork for the 
			identifying the resources to be protected, and what threats must be
			considered in the drafting of the Essential Security Requirements 
			(ESR) and for the TC to consider when writing the PP.
		-->
		<p> SSH is a network protocol provided by an application or an Operating System 
			to enable secure communications for management of <ul>
				<li>End user systems such as a desktop or laptop</li>
				<li>Server systems, which run on physical or virtual hardware</li>
				<li>Hardware devices, such as routers and switches</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</section>

	<section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
		<!-- 
    		This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the 
    		security problem by providing the reader with concise statements
    		regarding the scenarios in which the technology is being used. The 
    		intended usage presented here should lay the groundwork for the 
    		identifying the resources to be protected, and what threats must be
    		considered in the drafting of the Essential Security Requirements 
    		(ESR) and for the TC to consider when writing the PP.
    	-->
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li>Sensitive data transmited over the network.</li>
				<li>Sensitive data that is necessary to store in non-volatile memory.</li>
				<li>The configuration of the SSH client itself.</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</section>

	<section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess"> The following assumptions are made about
		attackers' ability to develop attacks: <ul>
			<li> An attacker has an arbitrary amount of time to analyze the behavior of SSH, its
				interaction with its platform, and the data it transmits over the network. </li>
			<li> An attacker is able to acquire their own copy of the target software and study its
				behavior on a platform that they control. </li>
		</ul>
		<p/> The attacker is expected to engage in the following general classes of attack:
		<ul>
			<li> Network eavesdropping, in which an attacker may monitor and gain access to data
				exchanged between the SSH Client and SSH Server. </li>
			<li> Network attack, in which an attacker may initiate malicious communications with an 
				SSH Client or Server or alter communications between the SSH Client and Server. </li>
			<li> Local attack, in which an attacker has gained the ability to execute code on the
				system, which may be used to escalate privilege or access data without
				authorization. </li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
		<!--
        	This is where the authors present an initial set of English 
        	requirements that specify security functionality, rather than 
        	design and/or implementation characteristics. These requirements 
        	will provide the foundation for which the detailed set of 
        	requirements is derived. It is important that the requirements 
        	captured here make an attempt to fully address the categories 
        	(e.g., access control, identification and authentication, 
        	management capabilities, roles of administration, secure 
        	communications, and audit). That's not to say the requirements are 
        	fully specified or detailed enough to simply translate to Common 
        	Criteria security functional requirements. The goal is that there 
        	is enough information contained here, as well as the other sections
        	of this document, to provide the TC enough information to ensure 
        	they have an understanding of what is minimally required in breath.
        -->
		<p> The following are the essential security requirements expected to be implemented by an
			SSH Client or Server within the established scope: 
			<ul>
				<li>SSH software shall implement the SSH protocol that complies with RFCs</li>
				<li>SSH transport implementation uses the following encryption algorithms:
					<ul>
					  <li>aes128-cbc</li>
					  <li>aes256-cbc</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>SSH connection be rekeyed after no more than 2^28packets have been transmitted</li>
			</ul>
			<ul>
				<li>Provide a trusted update mechanism to update itself<./li>
			</ul>
			<ul>
				<li>Provide strong authentication mechanisms.</li>
				<ul>
					<li>Support authentication methods as described in RFC 4252: public key-based, password-based</li>
				</ul>
			</ul>
		</p>
	</section>

	<section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
		<!--
			Simply put, this section presents the aspects of the product and 
			its	intended environment that can be assumed to hold true. This 
			will provide additional scope on the resulting PP.
		-->
		The following assumptions are made for the SSH Client or Server product and its operational environment:
	        <li>Administrators are not malicious in nature.</li>
	        <li>Users are not malicious in nature.</li>
	</section>


	<section title="Optional Extensions" id="extensions"> 
		None
	</section>

	<section title="Outside the TOE's Scope" id="outsidescope">
		<!--
			This is where the authors explicitly state things they do not want 
			to be considered for inclusion in an evaluation against a 
			resulting PP.  Items expressed here could include threats, 
			functions or capabilities that would require assurance activities 
			that are too subjective, or specific expertise not available in the
			evaluation facilities expected to assess products against the PP 
			(e.g., assessing anti-tamper measures). 
		-->
		The following list contains items that are explicitly out-of-scope for any evaluation
		against an SSH Client or Server <ul>
			<li>Malicious, Highly-Privileged Administrators - Highly-privileged administrators
				acting maliciously can disable most, if not all, security protections.
				Additionally procedural controls that are out of scope of this document should be
				considered to help highlight administrator accounts acting suspiciously.</li>
			<li>Zero Days - The disclosure of recently published vulnerabilities (Zero Days) should
				not be used as a reason to fail an SSH Client or Server undergoing evaluation.</li>
			<li>Unofficial Versions - Non-vendor supplied install images often contain added
				functionality and may weaken the normal operating functionality of the 
				SSH Client or Server.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
</ESR>
